A Guide to the Schroetter family papers, 1914-1918
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Schroetter family papers, 1914-1918
The Library of Virginia
51390
.9 cubic feet and 2 boxes
Schroetter family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased from Tim Abbott of Richmond, Virginia.
Biographical Information
Samuel Theodore Schroetter was born 24 January 1879 in Indiana to Ulrich Schroetter (1826-1899) and Mary Freyne Schroetter (1840-1899). Schroetter studied music under Conrad Ansorge and Earnest Jedliczka in Berlin, Germany, and graduated from the Stern Conservatory of Berlin. Schroetter returned to the United States and taught music at Virginia Intermont College. He became Director of Music at the school. He married Mabel Doak Morris (1890-1969) of Morristown, Tennessee, 30 August 1911, and they had one son. Schroetter died 10 December 1951 and is buried in Glenwood Cemetery in Bristol, Tennessee.
Mabel Doak Morris was born 23 July 1890 in Morristown, Tennessee, to Daniel C. Morris (1856-1930) and Sarah Etta Doak Morris (1868-1934). Mabel Morris attended Virginia Intermont College and after graduating, married Samuel Theodore Schroetter (1879-1951). She studied voice under Mrs. Fred Bacon (contralto) of Los Angeles, California; Clementi Bulogna (basso), of New York, New York; Frederic Martin (basso) of New York, and Sara Martin (contralto) of New York. She returned to Virginia Intermont College to teach voice, then later held other positions at the school. Mabel and Samuel Schroetter had one son. Mabel Schroetter died 1 July 1969 and was buried in Glenwood Cemetery in Bristol, Tennessee.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1914-1916, of the Schroetter family of Bristol, Virginia, consisting of correspondence between Samuel Theodore Schroetter (1879-1951) and Mabel Doak Morris Schroetter (1890-1969) while she was living in New York, New York and taking vocal lessons. Letters detail both Samuel's and Mabel's daily activities during their separation. Collection also includes the papers, 1918, of W. E. Hackley of Culpeper and Loudoun Counties, Virginia, consisting of a post card and an envelope and having no relation to the rest of the collection.
Samuel Theodore Schroetter's letters concern how much he loves and misses his wife and provide an account of life in Bristol while she is gone. He comments on events at Virginia Intermont College and on its faculty and students. He details his activities as a teacher, pianist and organist, both at the college and at First Baptist Church. He provides news about her family which resides in Morrisville, Tennessee, and about the faculity and student body. He also comments on the weather.
Mabel Morris Schroetter's letters concern how much she loves and misses her husband. She comments on her vocal training with Sara L. Martin and her life with Sara and Frederic Martin in New York City. She comments on the concerts, recitals, plays, and musical performances she attends and remarks on the various performers that she sees. She provides social news and comments on the weather. She also provides comments on social and family news.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Schroetter family papers, 1904-1954 (LVA accession 34003).
Contents List
- Letters, February-March 1914. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letters, September 1914. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letters, 25-26 October 1914. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letters, 27-28 October 1914. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letters, 29-31 October 1914. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letters, 1-4 November 1914. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letters, 5-7 November 1914. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letters, 8-10 November 1914. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letters, 12-14 November 1914. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Letters, 15-16 November 1914. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Letters, 18-20 November 1914. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Letters, 21-22 November 1914. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Letters, 23-26 November 1914. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Letters, 28-30 November 1914. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Letters, 1-2 December 1914. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Letters, 3-6 December 1914. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Letters, 7-8 December 1914. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Letters, 9-10 December 1914. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Letters, 11-13 December 1914. (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Letters, 15-18 December 1914. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Letters, 23 and undated December 1914. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Letters, 2-3 January 1915. (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Letters, 4-6 January 1915. (Box 1, Folder 23)